嘿，你们好，我是TheCherno，欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
hey, what's up guys, my name is TheCherno, welcome back to my OpenGL series
那么我想今天的内容可能比较酷比较有趣
so today's gonna be a pretty cool and fun episode I think
我们会整合一些叫做ImGui的东西
we're gonna be integrating something called ImGui
人们有不同的叫法比如ImGUI或ImgUi，我就叫它ImGui
ImGUI, ImgUi people say it differently, I say ImGui
但基本上ImGui就是一个GUI(图形用户接口)库
but basically what ImGui is is a GUI library
我们可以在OpenGL, DirectX，以及任何渲染接口中使用的东西
kind of thing that we can use in OpenGL, in DirectX, and any kind of rendering api
它是大多数接口是独立的，这是我们在屏幕上绘制UI(界面)的一种方式
it's pretty much api independent, it's a way for us to just draw UI on the screen
并且对于UI，我的意思就像按钮，文本框，拾色器之类的东西
and by UI, I mean things like buttons, text fields, color pickers
以及像那些的信息窗口，对调试非常有用
just information windows stuff like that, it's really really useful for debugging purposes
并且它甚至很有用
and it's even useful
如果你们想在实时渲染设置中快速制作一些应用
if you want to make some kind of application quickly in kind of a real time rendering setting
那么像图形编辑，可能比如我们在制作游戏引擎，我们希望能够在
so like a graphics edit, so maybe like if we were making a game engine, and we wanted to
不使用Qt制作Windows应用的情况下运行一个关卡编辑器
get a level editor up, and running without having to actually make a Windows application using Qt
或者使用WPF之类的
or WPF anything like that
你们甚至可以快速使用ImGui
you can even just make it using ImGui really quickly
它会像游戏一样运行，像实时应用一样运行，这很酷
and it would just run like a game, run like a real time application, which is really cool
那么ImGui的链接将在下面的描述中
so link to ImGui will be in the description below
今天这一期的想法基本上就是把它集成到我们现有的OpenGL代码库中
the idea for today's episode is just to basically integrated into our existing OpenGL code base
我们这么做的原因是为了以后
the reason we're doing this is because going forward
UI对我们非常有用
it's going to be really really useful for us to have a UI
为了调试的目的，我们可以快速地讲一下
kind of that we can just spin up really quickly for kind of debugging purposes
那么在屏幕上调出我们能看到和编辑的值会很容易
so for a it's going to be really easy for me to just bring up values on the screen that we can see and edit
然后看看这是如何影响我们的实际图像的
and then see that how that affects our actual graphics
但也对于调试，如果我们想要图形，如果我们想要帧率
but also for kind of debugging, if we want graphs, if we want frame rate
如果我们想要某种我们可以点击触发某些东西的按钮
if we want kind of buttons that we can click the trigger certain things
用ImGui库来实现那些真的很容易
it's really easy to kind of do all of that with with a library like ImGui
这样我们就不用编写新的UI库了，老实说，可能需要很长时间
and saves us having to write our new UI library, which to be honest, can take like really long time
所以不管怎样，废话少说，让我们进入正题，看看我们有些什么
so anyway, without further ado, let's just go in, and take a look at what we've got
那么如果我们只是运行我们的代码，看看上次我们做到了哪里
so if we guys are just running our code to see, where we were at last time
你们可以看到我们有这个ChernoLogo，我们有一个模型视图投影矩阵
you can see we had this ChernoLogo, and we had a model view projection matrix that we made
由投影矩阵组成
consisting of a projection matrix
那么视图矩阵和模型矩阵以及所有这些代码总是可以在github上获得
so view matrix and model matrix as always all this code is available on github
如果你们是我们的赞助人，请登录patreon.com/TheCherno
if you're a patron, so check out patreon.com/TheCherno
如果你们还没有，那就来注册获得每一期的所有代码吧
if you're not, and sign up to get all of this code individually per episode
那就是我们从模型视图投影那期开始的地方
that's where we're going to be starting from the kind of model view projection episode
所有这些代码都将成为这一期的基础
all that code is going to be the basis for this entire episode
好了，那么我们要做的第一件事是得到ImGui
okay, so the first thing we're going to do is get ImGui
所以如果你们查看描述中的链接或谷歌ImGui，我相信你们会找到它的
so if you check out the link in the description or just google ImGui, I'm sure you'll find it
如果我们去发布页面，我要下载1.6版本的源代码
if we go to the releases page here, I'm just going to download the source code for version 1.6
它是在12天前发布的，也就是制作这段视频的时候
it was released 12 days ago at the time of making this video
所以我要得到ImGui的这个版本的旧源代码的zip压缩包
so I'm just going to get the zip archive of old source code for this version of ImGui
一旦我找到那个，打开后，你们会看到imgui-1.6
once I've got that, if I open that, you'll see we have, imgui-1.6
现在这里有一些我们关心的东西
now there are a few things here that we care about
我们并不关心所有这些，你们可以看到，比如我们并不需要所有的例子
we don't care about all of this, like we don't really need all of the examples, you can see
从Apple到DirectX，有很多DirectX版本
there's everything here from Apple to DirectX, a bunch of DirectX versions
老式的OpenGL或现代的OpenGL，vulkan和sdl，有很多不同的东西
old school kind of OpenGL or modern OpenGL, vulkan and sdl and there's a lot of different things
我们并不关心这些，我们关心的是OpenGL3的例子
we don't care about a lot of these, what we do care about is at the OpenGL3 example
因为那个恰好用的是glfw，也就是我们现在用的
because that one happens to be using glfw, which is what we're using
并且那将使我们非常非常容易快速地集成它
and that's going to just make it really really easy for us to integrate it quickly
我们关心的另一件事是，当然实际是
and the other thing we care about is, of course the actual is
那么我们真正需要的基本上就是这些东西
so from is what we actually need is all this stuff basically
那么如果我就像那样复制所有这些cpp和头文件
so if I copy all of these kind of cpp header of files that we have here like that
所以就是所有这些，如果我复制它们，我要打开我的vendor文件夹
so that's all of them, if I copy them, I'm going to go ahead and open my vendor folder
并且然后从这里，我要创建一个名为imgui的文件夹
and then from here, I'm just going to make a folder called imgui
然后把所有的代码粘贴进去，那么我想要的另一个东西是glfw的例子
and then just paste in all of my code into there, so the other thing that I wanted was that glfw example
回到这个zip文件，打开examples文件夹
so if I go back to this zip file and into examples
glfw在哪里，那么就在opengl3_example文件夹中
and where is glfw, so opengl3
我只需要这两个，现在我们不需要main，我把它复制出来
I'm just gonna grab these two, now we don't really need main, I'll copy it out
不管怎样，我们不想要它，但它是一个很好的例子，我们可以用它
anyway, we don't want it or anything, but it is a good kind of example that we can just use
所以回到这里，把这些东西都粘贴进去
so if I go back here, I'll paste all this stuff in
至于main，再说一次，我们会删除的，可能不会包含在项目中
main, again, we're gonna delete, and we probably just won't include our project
但它仍然可以作为参考，好了，酷，所以那就是ImGui所需要的
but it's still useful to have there for reference, okay, cool, so that's all we need for ImGui
它非常非常容易设置
it's really really easy to set up
那么回到vendor，我会点击这里的刷新按钮
so go back to vendor, I'm just gonna hit this refresh button up here
在顶部，我将基本上包括这里的所有内容
at the top, and I'm going to basically include everything from here
我将排除那个main.cpp文件，因为我们不需要那个文件
I'm just going to exclude that one main.cpp file, because we do not want that
那么就是从项目中移除，但我们还是要把它放在这里作为参考
so exclude from project, but again we'll keep it around here for reference
好了，那么为了设置这个，如果我们看一下这个glfw的例子
okay, so to set this up, if we take a look at this glfw example here
它所做的一件事是它实际上使用gl3w而不是glew
one thing that it does is it actually uses gl3w instead of glew
我们要改变那个，所以去掉这个注释
we're just going to change that, so we'll get rid of this comment
我们把这个改成glew，我想，我也要把这个注释改一下
and we'll change this to be glew, and I guess, I'll change this comment here as well
差不多就这样，如果按ctrl f7，应该会编译，你们可以看到它是被编译了
that's pretty much it, if I hit ctrl f7, this should just compile, you can see it does
那么让我们试着编译整个项目
so let's try compiling the whole project
现在我们已经包含了所有这些ImGui文件，希望一切正常
now that we've included all of these ImGui files, hopefully everything works fine
并且如你们所见，好了，没有错误，我把输出窗口拖到这里
and as you can see, there we go, no errors, let me just drag this output window over here
没有错误，一切正常
no errors, everything is fine beautiful
那么现在我们只需要将它集成到我们的应用中，所以为了实现那个
so now we just need to integrate it into our application, so to do that
实现那个的一个很简单的方法是看一下我们排除的main.cpp文件
a really easy way to do that is just to take a look at this main.cpp file that we excluded
因为那里基本上有一个例子
because that basically has an example
所以这里我们需要做的就是为ImGui创建上下文
so really all we need to do here is we need to create the context for ImGui
我们需要调用这个GlfwGL3_Init
we need to call this GlfwGL3_Init
这个函数是在这个glfw_gl3例子中找到的
that function is found inside this glfw_gl3 example that they have here
并且你们可以看到，它注册了所有这些键绑定，它为我们处理这些
and you can see, it registers all of these kind of key bindings, it takes care of that for us
你们可以看到，我们要做的就是把window指针传递给GlfwGL3_Init
you can see that all we have to do is pass in the window pointer into a init
并且它会设置所有的输入绑定，所以它真的很酷
and it will just set up all of the input bindings, so it's really really cool
至于styleColorsDark，当然，为什么不呢
styleColorsDark, sure, why not
然后它调用了一些实际使用的例子
and then it's called some examples on actual uses
就像我们的运行循环一样，我们只需要开始一个新帧
just as for our run loop, we just need to start a new frame
并且在最后，我们只需要使用ImGui::Render()结束帧
and at the end, we just need to basically end the frame, using ImGui Render
然后是GlfwGL3_RenderDrawData，这就是所有的DrawData
and then RenderDrawData for Glfw3, and that's pretty much it, for all the DrawData
这样它就会使用OpenGL渲染它，最后我们可以调用shutdown
so that it actually renders it using OpenGL, and at the end we can do shutdown
并且差不多就这样了，那么如果我把这个并排停靠
and that's pretty much it, so if I just dock this side by side
让我们继续并开始复制其中的一些代码
let's go ahead and start copying some of this code
我把它缩小一点，希望你们能看到所有东西
I'm gonna zoom out a little bit, hopefully you guys can still see everything
在我复制这些东西的时候
this will just be for a bit while I copy this stuff
但基本上，让我们复制这儿这个CreateContext，并把它粘贴在顶部
but basically let's grab that CreateContext that we have here, and put it at the top
所以在我们做循环之前，也许在我们创建渲染器之后
so right before we do our loop here, maybe after we create the renderer
我会调用ImGui::CreateContext()
I'll call ImGui CreateContext
现在我们需要包含这个，因为它现在是在vendor文件夹
now we need to include this, because it's now vendor folder
我们应该能够做到包含imgui/imgui.h，还必须包含那个glfw3示例
we should just be able to do include imgui/imgui.h, and we'll also have to include that glfw3 example
所以就是这儿这个，好了，那么我们创建了上下文
so this one here great, okay, so we create the context
然后我们会初始化这个，那么我们会传入那个，你们可以看到
we're then going to initialize this, so we'll just pass that in, you can see
我的意思是
I mean
它的叫法甚至都是一样的，在两个例子中它都被称为window
it's even called the same, it's even called window in both examples
所以我们真的不需要改变任何事情
so we really literally don't have to change anything
我们将继续设置StyleColorsDark
we'll go ahead and set up that StyleColorsDark
初始化差不多就这样了
and that's it for the initialization
让我们直接开始一个新帧，这并不一定是
let's go ahead and start a new frame, now this doesn't have to be
这与开始一个新帧无关，就像一个新的glfw帧
this has nothing to do with starting a new frame, in terms of like a new glfw frame
这只是为了ImGui，所以我们可以把它放在这里
it's just for ImGui, so we can just put this here
没关系，我把它放在renderer.Clear()后
doesn't matter, I'll put it after the renderer clear
你们可以把它放在任何地方
you can put it anywhere
只要确保你们把它放在，比如在ImGui代码之间
just make sure you put it, like in between your ImGui code
所以在你们为这帧开始写任何ImGui代码之前，需要有新的帧函数调用
so before you start any ImGui code for this frame, you want to have the new frame function call
然后在最后，我要去渲染，然后绘制一个东西
and then at the end, there's I'm going render, and then that kind of draw out a thing
所以我会在交换缓冲区之前做这个，然后最后我们有一个shutdown
so I'll do that right before we swap the buffers, and then finally we have a shutdown
所以就是这两行代码，在glfwTerminate之前
so there's two lines for that, and that's right before glfwTerminate
我们把它放在这里，就那样，好了，现在让我们试着渲染一个窗口
we'll put it right there, that is it, okay, so now let's try and render a window
这个main的例子也是很漂亮的
this main example also has that which is beautiful
你们可以看到，这里有一个小窗口
you can see, there's a bit of a window over here
让我们复制那个把它放在，可能会把它放在渲染之后，那么也许在这里
let's copy that, I'll put it after, I might put it after we render everything, so maybe right over here
然后在顶部有一些我们也想复制的变量
and then there are a few variables at the top here that we want to also copy
让我们把它放在这里，让我们关闭main，把这个窗口还原
let's just put that here, and let's close main, I'll put the Texas back up
按f5，看看得到什么，好了，那么看一下，那很简单吧
let's hit f5, and see what we get, okay, so check that out, that was really easy
你们可以看到，现在我们有了这个窗口，我们可以四处移动它
and you can see, now what we have is this window, that we can kind of move around
并且所有的一切都很漂亮，那么我们还可以改变颜色
and everything's everything's pretty beautiful there, so we can change the color
我甚至可以点击这里，调整所有东西的颜色
I can even click over here, and adjust the color of everything
现在你们会注意到它和我的鼠标指针有一点偏移
now you'll notice that it is a bit offset from my mouse pointer
那实际上是因为这个笔记本电脑
that's actually this laptop
出于某种原因，window是dpi缩放的，我不知道，到底发生了什么
for some reason, window is dpi scaling or something, I don't know, exactly what's going on
但是鼠标指针对很多应用程序都存在偏移
but the mouse pointer is just offset for a lot of applications
如果我打开像Mischief软件，这是一个绘图应用
if I even open something like Mischief up, which is a paint drawing app
你们可以看到，当我在屏幕顶部时，它会偏离我的光标
you can see that it draws way offset from my cursor, when I'm at the top of the screen
然后如果我往下，它就会匹配，我不知道，你们能看到多少
and then if I kind of go down, it kind of matches, I don't know, how well you guys can see that
但没人知道到底发生了什么，这真的很令人沮丧
but anyone knows what on earth is going on here, it's been really frustrating
就是这台笔记本电脑
it's just this laptop
它不是唯一一种高分辨率的笔记本，我也有其他的
it's not the only kind of high resolution for whatever laptop, I've got either
所以我也不确定是什么原因
so I'm not sure why
但只是这台笔记本，这似乎是完全错误的，所以不要担心它
but it's just this one, that seems to be completely wrong, so don't worry about it
如果你正在做像我正在做的那样，应该完全没问题
if you're like your I'm doing, should be completely fine
但你们可以看到那个，是的，它甚至有拾色器
but you can see that, yeah, it's even got like color pickers
并且这只是这里的一个例子，然后还有所有这些设置
and this is just an example of kind of what you have here, and then all of these settings
就像，是的，我们可以拖动它，我们可以调整这个窗口的大小
and like, yeah, we can drag this around, we can resize this window
然而我只需要找到我的鼠标指针，这太烦人了，好了
however we like I just need to find my mouse pointer, this is so annoying, there we go
所以那就是我要继续做的，这是一个关于它是怎么运行的很好的例子
so yeah that's I'm going, this is a great example of how it works
现在让我们在代码中做一些有用的事情
now let's actually do something useful with it in our code
那么我把这些都删掉，我们这儿所有这些例子
so I'll get rid of all these, all this kind of example stuff that we have here
在整个示例窗口中，我们不需要
in this whole example window, we don't need
我会保留这个SliderFloat，因为它会很有用
one thing I will keep is this, I guess this SliderFloat, because that'll be useful
我会把所有东西都删掉，我想我们会保留帧率的东西
I'll get rid of everything, and I guess we'll keep this frame rate thing
因为这很有用，好了
because it's kind of useful, okay
那么现在我想做的一件事是，我们之前讨论过模型矩阵
so now one thing I want to do here is, we've just talked about model matrixes
以及如何用它们来变换实际的几何图形
and how we can use them to translate our actual geometry
让我们继续，把这个model矩阵改成我们可以实时编辑的那种
let's go ahead, and make this kind of model matrix something that we can actually edit live
所以为了实现那个，我要复制，基本上就是这两行代码
so to do that, I'm going to copy, basically these two lines
然后把它们粘贴到这里，就是我们实际提交统一变量的地方
and paste them over here, where we actually do our uniform submission
所以我们需要model矩阵，我们需要mvp，然后我要做的是
so we need the model metrix and we need the mvp, and then what I'll do with that is
我把这儿这个model矩阵和这儿这个mvp去掉
I'll just get rid of the model metrix from here and the mvp from here
我要剪贴mvp这行代码，这实际上是统一变量的设置
I'll cut this mvp line, this actually uniform setting
把它和其他统一变量放在一起
and I will put it over here with the other uniforms
所以现在我们基本上只是在每帧重新计算model和mvp，完全没问题
so now we're basically just recalculating the model matrix and the mvp every frame, which is totally fine
现在让我们添加一些东西到ImGui，让我们修改这个
so now let's add something to ImGui, lets us actually kind of modify this
那么现在它只是一个glm::vec3
so right now it's just a glm::vec3
并且那就是我们传递给这个glm::translatie的东西
and that's something that we're passing into this translate glm function
我会剪切那个，然后把它放到我们运行的循环之外
I'll cut that, and I'll put that outside of our run loop
那么也许在这里，我把这个叫做translation，还是(200, 200, 0)
so maybe over here, and I'll call this translation, we'll still start at a 200 200 and 0
如果我回到这里，粘贴translation
and if I go back here, I'll paste in translation
然后进入ImGui，我会使用一个叫做SliderFloat3的东西
and then into ImGui, I'll use something called a SliderFloat3
我们可能只用SliderFloat2，因为我们只关心x和y
we'll probably just use a float2, because we just care about x and y
但我们会使用SliderFloat3，我会传入translation.x的内存地址
but we'll use a SliderFloat3, and I'll pass in the memory address of translation.x
现在我不太确定这个的参数，你们可以看到，需要接收一个浮点数组
now I'm not really sure this takes a, you can see, this takes a float array
我不太确定如何把它从glm中找出来，如果我们看
I'm not really sure how to get that out of glm though, if we look at
如果我们看一下vec3是什么
if we look at what a vec3 is
它是lowp_vec3, highp_vec3，只是tvec3的别名
that's lowp_vec3, highp_vec3, is just a type def of tvec3
你们可以看到
you can see that
这里使用的是T x, y, z的联合体，T是浮点数，所以我们有了xyz
the thing that is using is just a union of T x y z, T is float, so we have xyz
差不多了，你们期望的vec3的布局是怎样的，当然是一个联合体
it's pretty much, how you would expect a vec3 to be laid out, the reason is a union of course
这样我们基本上就可以通过xyz或rgb或stp来定位它
just so that we can basically address it by the xyz or rgb or stp
不管我们想用什么变量名，它们的意思都是一样的
whatever kind of variable names we want to use, and they of course mean the same thing
但我什么都看不到，我之前看过这个
but I can't really see anything, I was looking through this a bit earlier
它返回一个实际的数组，就像一个指向所有东西的指针
that returns an actual array, like a pointer to everything
你们可以看到，它只返回T
you can see, this just returns T
所以我不太确定是否有办法
so I'm not exactly sure maybe there is a way
但现在，我要传递第一个变量的内存地址，也就是x或r
but right now, I'm just going to pass in the memory address of the first variable, which is x or r
不管你们想用什么，我就用x，那就给了它x的内存地址
whatever you want to use I'll just use x of course, and that's just going to give it the memory address of x
当然内存中的下一个是yz
and then of course the next one in memory is going to be yz there
因此，一切都将按照预期工作，因为内存布局与浮点数组相同
so everything will work as expected, because the memory layout is the same as a float array
好了，那么不管怎样，边界可能是0, 960
okay, so anyway, the bounds that will set are maybe 0, 960
因为我们有我们的投影矩阵，我想是960
because we have our projection matrix, I believe set to be up to 960
并且那就是我们要做的
and that's really all we have to do
我的意思是，这基本上是设置了之后我们可以使用的三个组件
I mean of course where this is basically setting up three components later that we can use
为了修改这个矢量tranlation，被传递到model，用于我们的mvp
to modify this translation vec3, which is being passed into model, and being used for our mvp matrix
我们把它传递到着色器中，那么所有的东西都连接起来了
which we pass into our shader, so everything is kind of linking up
如果我们按f5来运行这里的代码，你们可以看到我们得到的是这个
if we hit f5 to run out code here, you can see what we get is this
如果我把这个窗口移到一边一点
and if I move this window out to the side a little bit
我能做的就是改变这儿这个值，也就是x的位置
what I can do is change the this value here, this is the x position
这是y的位置，你们可以看到它移动了所有的东西，对吧
this is the y position, and you can see that it moves everything, right
如果我把所有的都换成0，你们可以看到，它并不是很靠近底部
and if I put everything to 0 0, you can see, it's not really quite the bottom here
那将是，因为我认为在我们的顶点缓冲中
and that would be, because I think in our vertex buffer
是的，你们可以看到，我们并没有触底
yeah, you can see, we don't actually hit the bottom anywhere
这里是100x200，这便是为什么它不在左下角的原因
we're kind of at 100 by 200, so that is why that's not in the very kind of bottom left
不管怎样，是的，这就是为什么ImGui总是很有用的一个很好的例子
anyway, yeah, that's a great example of why ImGui always really useful
它能让我们快速地调出这个，当代码运行时，我们能控制这些东西
it just lets us quickly bring up stuff like this, that we can control while our actual code is running
所以我们不需要一直重新编译
so we don't have to keep recompiling
它真的会帮助我展示一些我们在这个系列中涉及到的东西
and it's really going to help me to show some of this things that we cover in this series
更详细一点，不幸的是，我讨厌鼠标偏移
in a bit more detail, now unfortunately, I hate this mouse offset thing
也许我可以考虑下次解决
maybe I can actually think about solving that for next time
但我希望你们喜欢这个视频，如果喜欢的话，就为它点赞吧
but I hope you guys enjoyed this video, if you did you hit the like button
你们也可以通过访问patreon.com/TheCherno来帮助支持这个系列
you can also help support the series by going to patreon.com/TheCherno
像往常一样，每期视频的代码都会放在github上
as always, like every the code for every video goes up on github
如果你们是赞助人，就可以访问它，所以一定要看看这个代码
and if you're a patron, you can access that, so be sure to take a look at this code
如果你们想确保没有犯任何错误或类似的事情
if you want to make sure you didn't make any errors or anything like that
集成ImGui真的很简单
it was really simple to integrate ImGui
我的意思是你们看到了它有多容易，真的没什么大不了的
I mean you saw how easy it was, really no big deal
如果我是在编写自己的引擎，我可能会重写他们的glfw
if I was kind of writing my own engine, I probably may have rewritten their kind of glfw thing
为了包括其他像DirectX或任何我想支持的接口
to also include other apis like DirectX or whatever I supported
这个系列显然是关于OpenGL的，我只是想ImGui
so this series is obviously just about OpenGL, I just thought ImGui
因为它会帮助我更容易地解释很多OpenGL概念
because it's gonna help me explain a lot of OpenGL concepts a lot easier
因为我可以实时控制东西
because I can kind of manipulate things live
但是不管怎样，下节课，我们会继续下节课的内容
but anyway, next time, what we're gonna move on to next time
有这么多内容要讲，你们只能等到下次了
that is just so much to cover, you'll have to just wait until next time
看看最后会发生什么，到时候见，再见
and see what ends up happening, I'll see you then, goodbye